Register of the Thomas St. John Gaffney Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Thomas St. John Gaffney Papers
1887-1941
XX227
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (3.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to international relations, the World War I war guilt question, reparations, Irish independence, American domestic politics and foreign policy, and Jews. Includes correspondence with Kaiser Wilhelm II in exile, Baron Hermann Speck von Sternberg (German ambassador to the United States), and Jules Cambon (French ambassador to Germany). Also available on microfilm (5 reels).
Gaffney, Thomas St. John, 1864-1945
Access
Originals closed. Microfilm use copies available.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1942.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (5 reels).
Related Materials
Sir Roger Casement Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1864 Born, Limerick, Ireland
1882 Came to the United States
1889 Admitted to the New York Bar
1897 President, Patriotic League of America
Circa 1900 Co-author with Joseph Smith, American in the Orient: The United States, Russia, and France and the Anglo-Japanese Treaty
1902 Named Chevalier of the Legion of Honor by French President émile Loubet
1905 Conferred by King Leopold of Belgium with the officer's cross of the order of Leopold II
1905-1913 Consul General for Dresden, appointed by President Theodore Roosevelt
1913-1915 Consul General for Munich, appointed by President Woodrow Wilson
1915 November Forced to resign after making partisan statements in support of Germany
1930 Author, Breaking the Silence: England, Ireland, Wilson and the War
1945 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains materials largely pertaining to the war guilt question after WWI, reparations, Irish independence, American domestic politics and foreign policy, Jews, and the activities of Kaiser Wilhelm II in exile. After his forced resignation in 1915, Gaffney returned to Germany a number of times and continued his interactions with German officials and other diplomats. Although Gaffney's relationship with Sir Roger Casement was one of the motivating factors for his resignation, the collection contains little on the Irish nationalist.
Gaffney's Correspondence provides the most information into the breadth of his political interests and activities from before his appointment as consul general to after the publication of his memoir Breaking the Silence. Of particular note in this series is a letter to Herbert Hoover in 1929 regarding war guilt and reparations, punctuated with a handwritten note by Kaiser Wilhelm II.
The Scrapbooks series contains correspondence, clippings, and photographs compiled by Gaffney documenting his relationship with Kaiser Wilhelm II in exile in Doorn. Loose items filed within the scrapbook pages were left in place.
The biographical materials in the Clippings and Collected materials series are comprised of articles by and about Gaffney printed in American and German newspapers. Among the collected materials filed by subject in this series are German propaganda flyers from WWI published by the Fichte-Bunde and distributed in the United States.
Gaffney's Speeches and Writings focus mostly on his interpretations of the War Guilt Clause in the Treaty of Versailles and its implications on Germany and German-Americans. The researcher should be aware that some writings are under the pen name Arthur Fleming. Additional writings are filed by subject in the Clippings and Collected materials series.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 4 series: Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Clippings and Collected materials, and Scrapbooks
Cambon, Jules Martin, 1845-1935.; Sternburg, Hermann Speck von, Freiherr, 1852-1908.; William II, German Emperor, 1859-1941.; Diplomats--United States.; Germany--Foreign relations--United States.; Great Britain--Foreign relations.; Ireland--History--20th century.; Jews.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918--Reparations.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Correspondence, 1887-1941 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of letters, invitations, and enclosures.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by last name
  - General, 1890-1940 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Unidentified, 1903-1934 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Bethmann-Hollweg, Theobald von, 1917 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1924-1933 (Folder 1: 4)
    Includes enclosed correspondence regarding William Dodd
  - Belgian Legation, 1902 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Bigelow, Poultney, 1930 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Boehm-Tettelbach, Hans W., 1931 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Borah, William E., 1928 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Bothmer, Felix von Reichsgraf, 1931 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Cambon, Jules, 1900-1903 (Folder 1: 10)
    See also Scrapbooks
  - Carter, Boake, 1940 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Carter, Frederic, 1887 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Chamberlain, Neville, 1938 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Cohalan, Daniel F., 1931 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Copeland, Royal S., 1931 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Dieckhoff, Hans Heinrich, 1938 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Draeger, Phil H.C. Hans, 1931-1936 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Emerson, Edwin, 1931 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Epp, Franz Ritter von, 1935-1936 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Fein, Claus, 1936 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Frick, Wilhelm, 1933 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Gerard, James Watson, 1915 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Gibbons, James, Cardinal, 1915 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Hitler, Adolf, 1931-1933 (Folder 1: 24)
    Includes responses from secretary of Wilhelm Bruckner
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1928-1931 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Jagow, Kurt, 1929 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Kasenkamp, Georg, 1932 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Kiep, Otto Carl, 1933 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Lössl, Edler von and Sigmund Ritter, 1915 (Folder 1: 29)
  - McDonald, J. Ramsey, 1929 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Papen, Franz von, 1932 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Reichenau, Walther von, 1929 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Rochambeau, René? de, 1902 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Roddie, Stewart, undated (Folder 1: 34)
  - Rudi, 1897-1898 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Russell, Charles, 1903 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Russian Imperial embassy, Washington, 1902 (Folder 1: 37)
  - St. Clair, C.M., 1934-1935 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Soden, G., 1925-1927 (Folder 1: 39)
  - South African Republic embassy, Brussels, 1900 (Folder 1: 40)
  - Schnee, M., 1931 (Folder 1: 41)
  - Sell, Ulrich von, 1933, 1938 (Folder 1: 42)
    See also Scrapbooks--Kaiser Wilhelm II in exile
  - Shipstead, Henrik, 1928-1929 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Sternburg, Hermann Speck von, 1902-1908 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Stoddard, John L., 1915-1917 (Folder 1: 45)
  - Sullivan, Mark, 1933 (Folder 1: 46)
  - Wegerer, Alfred von, 1934 (Folder 1: 47)
  - William II, 1929-1941 (Folder 1: 48)
  - Letters of gratitude for helping English and Americans in Munich, 1915-1916 (Folder 1: 49)
  - Miscellaneous invitations, 1891-1928 (Folder 1: 50)
- Speeches and writings, 1900-1933, undated (Box 1-2)
  Consists of typescript and handwritten drafts of writings, and some printed copies
  Arranged chronologically
  - Untitled writings on misrepresentation of Germany in the foreign press, Vatican and Dresden Courts, Irish and Italian immigrants in the United States, and Kaiser Wilhelm II, undated (Folder 1: 51)
  - "American Intervention in Russia in 1918: The Lytton Report,", undated (Folder 1: 52)
  - "An Appeal to the Conscience of America, handwritten and typescript drafts, undated (Folder 1: 53-54)
  - "End of the Fantastic Reparation Claims of the Allies,", undated (Folder 1: 55)
  - "England's Guilt and England's Hypocrisy: An American Verdict,", undated (Folder 1: 56)
  - "The League of Nations and the Reconciliation of the Peoples," draft, undated (Folder 1: 57)
  - Letter to the editor, The Herald Tribune, handwritten draft, undated (Folder 1: 58)
  - Letter to the editor, The New York Sun, undated (Folder 1: 59)
  - "New York in Danger of Jewish Domination,", undated (Folder 1: 60)
  - "Notes and comments,", undated (Folder 1: 61)
  - "The Origin of the Guilt Clause of the Versailles Treaty the Responsibility of Secretary of State Lansing and James Brown Scott,", undated (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Wilsonism Dominant in Chicago,", undated (Folder 2: 2)
  - "The Alleged European Coalition, Against the United States During the Spanish-American War," printed copy, 1900 (Folder 2: 3)
  - "The Anglo-Japanese Treaty: A Last Work on Pauncefote--His American Champions Utterly Routed--British Duplicity During the Spanish War," printed copy, 1900 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Letter to the editor, New York World, 1915 August 24 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Reports from Munich as consul general, 1915 (Folder 2: 6)
  - "The Alleged Potsdam War Crown Council of July 5, 1914, Sweeping Repudiation of the Myth By the Kaiser,", after 1915 (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Morgenthau's Potsdam War Council Exposed as a Fake in the 'Suddeutsche Monatshefte,'", circa 1918 (Folder 2: 8)
  - "'Terrorism' in Our Own Ranks, Instances of Unexampled Brutality Practiced on American Doughboys During and After the War by Martinets Who Criticize Conditions in German Labor Camps," Deutsche Zeitung, after 1919 (Folder 2: 9)
  - "The German Americans During the World War," speech at the Concord Society of America, 1926 November 28 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Letter to the editor, The Commonweal, 1928 August 6 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Letter to the editor, Herald Tribune, "Reparations and the War Guilt Problem,", 1929 April 26 (Folder 2: 12)
  - "The Kaiser Repudiates the Potsdam Conference 'Legend,'" Current History, 1930 February (Folder 2: 13)
  - "War Guilt Commission," Current History, 1930 March (Folder 2: 14)
  - Letter to the editor, North American Review, 1932 August 1 (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Immigration and the Crime Wave," The Commonweal, 1932 September 28 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Writings published in American Monthly, 1932-1933 (Folder 2: 17)
  - "The Siberian Adventure of Woodrow Wilson, More About the Red Cross," American Monthly, 1933 January (Folder 2: 18)
  - Letter to the editor, Evening Post, 1933 April 8 (Folder 2: 19)
  - "An Open Letter," Observer's Post, 1933 May 1 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Letter to the editor, The Herald Tribune, 1933 June 4 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Quotations and notes, undated (Folder 2: 22)
- Clippings and Collected materials, 1897-1940 (Box 2-3: 51)
  Consists of clippings from newspapers and journals, writings, and correspondence
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Africa, 1929 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Atrocities and war conduct, 1917-1940 (Folder 2: 24-25)
  - Belgium, 1928 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Biographical (Folder 2)
    - Undated (Folder 2: 27)
    - 1897-1905 (Folder 2: 28)
    - 1911-1915 (Folder 2: 29)
    - 1916-1919 (Folder 2: 30)
    - 1920-1924 (Folder 2: 31)
    - 1925-1929 (Folder 2: 32)
    - 1930-1932 (Folder 2: 33)
    - 1933 (Folder 2: 34)
    - 1934-1936 (Folder 2: 35)
    - 1939 (Folder 2: 36)
  - Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1933 (Folder 2: 37)
  - Canada, 1918, undated (Folder 2: 38)
  - Church, 1915-1936 (Folder 2: 39)
  - England, 1914-1940 (Folder 2: 40-41)
  - France, 1917-1933 (Folder 3: 1-2)
  - German-Americans, 1934 (Folder 3: 3)
  - German propaganda, 1925-1926, undated (Folder 3: 4-5)
  - Germany, 1914-1933 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Hitler, Adolf, 1933-1940 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Ireland, undated (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Jewish question,", 1931-1933 (Folder 3: 9-10)
  - League of Nations, 1919-1930 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Lloyd George, David, undated (Folder 3: 12)
  - Neutrality, 1918 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Poems, undated (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Propaganda and lies,", 1914-1925 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Reparations, undated (Folder 3: 16)
  - Russia, 1931 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Shipstead, Henrik, 1928-1929 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Treaties (Folder 3:)
    - General, 1918-1927 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Revision, 1930-1933 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Versailles, 1921-1931 (Folder 3: 21)
  - United States and war, 1918-1931 (Folder 3: 22)
  - War guilt, 1926-1931 (Folder 3: 23-24)
  - Wile, Frederic William, 1928 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1916-1932 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Miscellany, 1914, undated (Folder 3: 25)
- Scrapbooks, 1893-1940 (Box 4-5: 22)
  Contains clippings, correspondence, invitations, menus, postcards, and photographs
  Arranged by topic or form
  - Correspondence and invitations, 1893-1902 (Folder 4: 1-4)
    2 scrapbooks
  - Personal and biographical clippings, 1899-1905 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Kaiser Wilhelm II in exile (A), 1927-1939 (Folder 4: 6-7)
  - Kaiser Wilhelm II in exile (B), 1927-1937 (Folder 5: 1-3)
  - Breaking the Silence reviews and related correspondence, 1931-1940 (Folder 5: 4-5)